<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Seascapemodels</title>
<link>https://www.seascapemodels.org/bluecology_blog.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://www.seascapemodels.org/bluecology_blog.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.8.25</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 13:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Keeping files organised for publication</title>
  <link>https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2026-02-19-keeping-organised-for-publication/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Getting files ready for publication can be frustrating when you can’t find the right file, or you realize your figures look like 2000s jpeg.</p>
<p>Here’s a list of things I wished I’d done (or my students had done) properly earlier in the paper prep process. Save this list somewhere to refer back to it, it will save you time and frustration.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Keep folders organized. Save figures for the pub to a single folder. Likewise have a folder for tables. Towards submission label these files as per the paper e.g.&nbsp;fig1_concepts.png ….</p></li>
<li><p>You R scripts should save plots directly to that folder like ggsave(“plots/fig1-lineplot.png…)</p></li>
<li><p>If assembling figures in powerpoint, save original powerpoint in this folder also</p></li>
<li><p>Always save figures in high res .png format, ready for publication. e.g.&nbsp;ggsave(“plots/bias_sensitivity_analysis.png”, final_plot, width = 12, height = 6, dpi = 300)</p></li>
<li><p>Have separate R scripts that make pub ready figures (e.g.&nbsp;load final model fits and make figures). This way you can quickly go back into and edit them. Obviously make the scripts easy to find with clear names and project folder structure.</p></li>
<li><p>Even better save both .png and .pdf versions. Never use .jpg (.jpg is for photos)</p></li>
<li><p>When revising your ms to respond to reviews turn on track changes the entire time. You should resubmit the track changed version as one of the files.</p></li>
<li><p>Double check how coauthors spell their names/institutions against their previous papers, before you submit</p></li>
</ul>



 ]]></description>
  <category>research</category>
  <category>rstats</category>
  <guid>https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2026-02-19-keeping-organised-for-publication/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 13:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Signalling credible publications to editors</title>
  <link>https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2026-02-10-signalling-credible-publications/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Generative AI is removing the writing barrier to publication. Quality writing was one of the signals that editors and reviewers used to differentiate high quality from low quality work. But now its easy to produce low quality work that is well written.</p>
<p>As AI slop becomes more ubiquitous the publication system will need to look for new signals for quality research. The quality of the data may be one signal.</p>
<p>Author names and status may be another.</p>
<p>News from the cybersecurity world provides an interesting hint as to how the future of publication may look.</p>
<p>Many widely open source software packages allow for anyone to flag security flaws. Sometimes they offer bounties or rewards for identifying flaws. But genAI coding agents have flooded these projects with submissions, most of them AI slop. <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2026/01/21/curl_ends_bug_bounty/">This creates a huge burden on the software maintainers to manage and filter through those submissions</a>.</p>
<p><a href="https://simonwillison.net/2026/Feb/7/vouch/">A recently proposed system for ‘vouching’</a> allows the software maintainers to create a list of verified contributors. It effectively creates a list of allowed contributors to an open software project. If you aren’t ‘vouched’ you are blocked from contributing.</p>
<p>The issue with submissions on software security is much like the trends we are hearing about at peer-reviewed journals of increasing numbers of well-written but vacuous studies.</p>
<p>So maybe in the near future we’ll have to get our names on a white list before we can submit to reputable journals.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>research</category>
  <category>genAI</category>
  <guid>https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2026-02-10-signalling-credible-publications/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 13:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Benefits of doing community and academic service as a researcher</title>
  <link>https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2026-02-05-benefits-of-doing-a-service-role/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Service can take many forms. You might serve on a student representative committee, an ethics or occupational health and safety committee, or teaching review panels. You could join advisory committees for marine protected areas or other conservation initiatives. You might give presentations and webinars to educate practitioners or other researchers about new methods.</p>
<p>In our lab meeting recently we discussed the types and benefits of service. Here’s some of the insights from that conversation.</p>
<section id="ideas-for-service-roles" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="ideas-for-service-roles">Ideas for service roles</h2>
<p>Here’s a list of some of the suggestions the lab had</p>
<ul>
<li>Academic committees e.g.&nbsp;health and safety, ethics</li>
<li>Conference organising committees</li>
<li>Committee of professional societies</li>
<li>Student representative to the department or university executive</li>
<li>Advisory roles, like marine parks advisor or fishery advisor</li>
<li>Peer-review of non-academic material, e.g.&nbsp;government analyses or reports</li>
<li>Community outreach and education for your institution</li>
<li>Science communication, e.g.&nbsp;via YouTube</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="meeting-people-and-building-community" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="meeting-people-and-building-community">Meeting people and building community</h2>
<p>Service roles put you in rooms with people you wouldn’t normally work with. We’ve met conservation practitioners, government scientists, industry representatives, and researchers from completely different fields through service work. These connections have enriched my understanding of how research fits into broader contexts.</p>
<p>Building community also helps to create a support system. The people you meet through service can become collaborators, mentors, or simply colleagues who understand the challenges you face.</p>
</section>
<section id="learning-about-funding-opportunities" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="learning-about-funding-opportunities">Learning about funding opportunities</h2>
<p>Being on advisory committees gives you insider knowledge about funding. You learn what funders are looking for, what makes a strong application, and sometimes you hear about opportunities before they’re widely advertised. This context is invaluable when you’re preparing your own grant applications.</p>
</section>
<section id="having-real-world-impact" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="having-real-world-impact">Having real-world impact</h2>
<p>Some service roles let you see direct outcomes from your work. Team members have been involved in advising on marine protected areas that were subsequently designated. That’s a tangible conservation outcome that came from service work, not from publishing papers. These experiences remind us why we got into research in the first place.</p>
</section>
<section id="developing-organizational-skills" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="developing-organizational-skills">Developing organizational skills</h2>
<p>Service roles teach you how organizations actually work. You learn how decisions get made, how to navigate bureaucracy, and how to work with diverse stakeholders. These are skills that don’t come from lab work or data analysis, but they’re essential for being an effective researcher.</p>
</section>
<section id="strengthening-your-cv" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="strengthening-your-cv">Strengthening your CV</h2>
<p>Service roles differentiate you from other applicants when you’re applying for jobs or promotions. They show you’re a good community citizen who contributes beyond your own research program. Selection panels notice this.</p>
</section>
<section id="strategic-alignment-with-your-research" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="strategic-alignment-with-your-research">Strategic alignment with your research</h2>
<p>You can be strategic about which service roles you take on. Choose committees or advisory roles that align with your research interests. The synergies can help you you get new ideas, opportunities, and perspectives that feed directly back into your research. You also build networks with people working on similar problems.</p>
</section>
<section id="taking-a-break-from-research" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="taking-a-break-from-research">Taking a break from research</h2>
<p>That being said, sometimes it’s valuable to take on service that’s completely different from your day-to-day research. It can be refreshing to do work that’s well outside your research area, like volunteering for a local community group. These roles give you a mental break while still being productive.</p>
</section>
<section id="a-few-caveats" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-few-caveats">A few caveats</h2>
<p>Not all service roles are equally valuable. Some committees meet endlessly without accomplishing much. Try to choose roles where you can see clear outcomes and where your contribution will matter.</p>
<p>Service work often goes unrecognized in academic promotion systems that prioritize publications and grants. Make sure you’re documenting your service contributions and that they’re visible in your CV and promotion applications.</p>
<p>Consider the time commitments. Some service roles can be time consuming. But many others can be impactful and require relatively little investment of time. Committees often meet once a month or fortnight for instance, which is a small contribution in the scheme of other research tasks.</p>
</section>
<section id="final-thoughts" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="final-thoughts">Final thoughts</h2>
<p>Service roles have connected me with practitioners, exposed me to new ideas, and given me opportunities to have real-world impact. They’ve made me a better researcher and a more engaged member of the scientific community. If you’re considering a service role, I’d encourage you to give it a try. Just be strategic about what you take on and make sure it aligns with your career goals and available time.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>research</category>
  <guid>https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2026-02-05-benefits-of-doing-a-service-role/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 13:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Reading for new quantitative ecology PhD students</title>
  <link>https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2020-02-18-new-phd-reading-quant-ecol/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Here is my recommended reading list for students just starting a PhD in some aspect of quantitative ecology. I’ve written this reading list to keep in mind that many new PhDs may not have a lot of math or stats from their earlier degrees.</p>
<p>Refreshing this from 2020 to 2026!</p>
<section id="the-role-of-statistics-in-science" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-role-of-statistics-in-science">The role of statistics in science</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/books/cause-and-correlation-in-biology/247799189B31939D24BC0F61FD59E9BB">Shipley, Cause and Correlation in Biology</a></p>
<p>Chapters 1 and 2 give a general introduction to the modern philosophy of science, with a focus on statistics, cause and correlation. This is a great introduction to how we use correlation to infer causation in modern science, and how science often progresses by building evidence for or against multiple competing hypotheses.</p>
<p>Chapters 3 onwards are more focused on the methods of structural equation modelling and will be of most interest to students who will be using statistical models such as GLMs.</p>
<p><a href="https://press.princeton.edu/books/paperback/9780691034973/the-ecological-detective">Hilborn and Mangel, The Ecological Detective</a></p>
<p>The first few chapters are worth reading for an excellent introduction to the philosophy of science. Later chapters focus on theory and application of Bayesian statistical methods.</p>
<p><a href="https://academic.oup.com/jrsssa/article/180/4/967/7068392?login=false">Gelman Hennig, Beyond Subjective and Objective in Statistics</a></p>
<p>Great paper that explores the role of subjective decision making statistics (hint, its much more than you might think!) and suggests improved language and ways of thinking about objectivity.</p>
</section>
<section id="bayesian-statistics" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="bayesian-statistics">Bayesian Statistics</h2>
<p><a href="https://xcelab.net/rm/statistical-rethinking/">McElreath, Statistical Rethinking</a></p>
<p>If you are going to be doing anything with Bayesian methods, then this book is gold. McElreath uses easily understood analogies to break down the jargon and complexity of Bayesian models and make them accessible to a general science audience.</p>
<p>You can even <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4WVelCswXo4">watch this whole book</a> in his lecture series on YouTube.</p>
</section>
<section id="ecological-modelling" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="ecological-modelling">Ecological modelling</h2>
<p><a href="https://press.princeton.edu/books/hardcover/9780691123448/a-biologists-guide-to-mathematical-modeling-in-ecology-and-evolution">Otto and Day, A biologists guide to mathematical modelling in Ecology and Evolution</a>.</p>
<p>I’d recommend the first few chapters for everyone again, because they will give you a good overview of what modelling is about. Later chapters will be good for students who will be specifically using process models (e.g.&nbsp;with differential equations) in their PhD.</p>
</section>
<section id="data-visualisation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="data-visualisation">Data visualisation</h2>
<p>There are lots of great books on this topic, but one of my favourites is <a href="http://www.thefunctionalart.com/p/the-truthful-art-book.html">Cairo, The Truthful Art</a>.</p>
<p>Cairo uses really compelling examples to show how we can use data visualisation and simple statistics to accurately communicate scientific knowledge.</p>
</section>
<section id="skills-for-a-successful-phd" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="skills-for-a-successful-phd">Skills for a successful PhD</h2>
<p>You can’t go past <a href="https://www.ithinkwell.com.au/bookshop/phd-book-set">Gardiner and Kearn’s books</a>. There’s a whole bunch to recommend here, but the Seven Secrets is probably a good place to start.</p>
</section>
<section id="your-field-of-study" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="your-field-of-study">Your field of study</h2>
<p>You should of course be also reading papers in your specific field of study. A few tips for finding these are:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Look in the top review journals, like Trends in Ecology and Evolution and Biological Reviews, for recent articles in your general area of interest. These journals in particular have high communication standards and articles are pitched at a more general audience than in specialist journals.</p></li>
<li><p>Search (e.g.&nbsp;with web of science) for review articles on your topic in discipline specific journals. For instance, if its conservation planning, then look in Conservation Letters, Conservation Biology and Biological Conservation.</p></li>
<li><p>Make sure you read the new and old literature. One way to identify very influential older papers is to sort results of a lit search by citation count. When you start your PhD you have your chance to read some of the classics. You probably won’t feel you have time to read this sort of thing later on (though don’t let me hold you back if you want to!).</p></li>
<li><p>Ask your peers for their favourite papers to read.</p></li>
<li><p>Follow up on citations. For instance, if you see an article that is repeatedly cited</p></li>
</ol>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>research-skills</category>
  <guid>https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2020-02-18-new-phd-reading-quant-ecol/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jan 2026 13:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>An ecologist’s reading list for Tasmanian reefs</title>
  <link>https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2026-01-17-ecologists-reading-list-tassie-reefs/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>A new research student at my institution recently asked me “what should I read to learn about the ecology of Tasmania’s reef ecosystems?”</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2026-01-17-ecologists-reading-list-tassie-reefs/trumpeter-in-kelp.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Image: Bastard Trumpeter (fish) in a giant kelp forest in Tasmania</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>By reefs I’m thinking of the shallow reefs that are within diveable depth, so &lt;40 metres. Basically, what you might see if you go diving or snorkeling down here.</p>
<p>There’s so much natural history to tell, but I can’t think of a single great source to recommend for an introduction. Writing that guide would be a great project for someone (and let me know if you know of one already).</p>
<p>The palawa are the first inhabitants of Tasmania and their claim to the land and seas was never ceded. If you know of good resources for Tasmanian Aboriginal relationship to the oceans, please let me know. In the meantime, I recommend you visit the Tasmanian Museum and Art Gallery and tour their exhibition on palawa culture.</p>
<p>Here’s a list of studies that cover some background on ecology in their content. Most are related to climate change, because that has been a big issue here in Tasmania, and therefore a big research theme. Feel free to comment or write me if you have other studies you think I should add here.</p>
<p>Many of these are scientific articles (again, we really need someone to pull this together into an accessible book or web resource). Some of the articles are paywalled, so if you can’t get them, I recommend emailing the lead author (you will find their emails on the paper webpages).</p>
<p>Graham Edgar has written a number of books on marine life. Most are ID guides, but they are also have some information on general ecology. Here are two I recommend:</p>
<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Australian-Marine-Habitats-Temperate-Waters/dp/1876334533">Australian marine habitats in temperate waters</a>. Graham Edgar</p>
<p><a href="https://underwater.com.au/shop/australian-marine-life.html">Australian Marine Life.</a> Graham Edgar</p>
<p>Many years ago Edgar also wrote a general paper for the Royal Society of Tasmania on reef ecology:</p>
<p><a href="https://doi.org/10.26749/rstpp.118.173">Edgar, GJ (1984). General features of the ecology and biogeography of Tasmanian subtidal rocky shore communities. University Of Tasmania. Journal contribution. https://doi.org/10.26749/rstpp.118.173</a></p>
<p>Its old, but the basic ecology is still relevant.</p>
<p>A big feature of the reefs are the interactions among rock lobster, sea urchins and kelp forests. This study describes that interaction:</p>
<p><a href="https://www.pnas.org/doi/abs/10.1073/pnas.0907529106">Ling SD, Johnson CR, Frusher SD, Ridgway K. Overfishing reduces resilience of kelp beds to climate-driven catastrophic phase shift. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences. 2009 Dec 29;106(52):22341-5.</a></p>
<p>And a more recent update:</p>
<p><a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-023-44543-x">Ling SD, Keane JP. Climate-driven invasion and incipient warnings of kelp ecosystem collapse. Nature communications. 2024 Jan 9;15(1):400.</a></p>
<p>Reading modelling studies, rather than directly empirical studies, is actually a great way to get an overview of what’s understood about ecology. Modellers need to synthesize a large number of concepts into a simple representation. This modelling study is a good place to start:</p>
<p><a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1111/gcb.13285?casa_token=zZ1l8FwzoKkAAAAA%3AVMa8gfRmQdNKDnUlbACDvhUewwz-xBHlhfrDj7uchz-xJeY-RBB67RyRJHmpPpzRu2hGeQ94MVQ00lHZ">Marzloff et al.&nbsp;2016 Modelling marine community responses to climate-driven species redistribution to guide monitoring and adaptive ecosystem-based management</a>Global Change Biology</p>
<p>Species changing their ranges due to warming ocean temperatures have been big driver of change over the past two decades. Here’s a few key studies on that topic:</p>
<p><a href="https://royalsocietypublishing.org/rspb/article/284/1856/20170484/78501/Biological-interactions-both-facilitate-and-resist">Bates et al.&nbsp;2017 Biological interactions both facilitate and resist climate-related functional change in temperate reef communities Proc B</a></p>
<p><a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jembe.2011.02.032">Johnson et al.&nbsp;2011 Climate change cascades: Shifts in oceanography, species’ ranges and subtidal marine community dynamics in eastern Tasmania JEMBE</a></p>
<p><a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1111/j.1466-8238.2010.00575.x?casa_token=P5yeDk_vNLkAAAAA%3AyFqHNL3y6eOPpnI5tga8lvVYxKmlFts2xg6hGDgTVrmQV4d3htsh18ZVbU_NWvMrh0sxS-lXv_-H1Jo4">Last et al.&nbsp;2010 Long-term shifts in abundance and distribution of a temperate fish fauna: a response to climate change and fishing practices GEB</a></p>
<p><a href="https://connectsci.au/mf/article-abstract/61/9/963/59057/Climate-driven-range-changes-in-Tasmanian?redirectedFrom=fulltext">Pitt NR, Poloczanska ES, Hobday AJ. Climate-driven range changes in Tasmanian intertidal fauna. Marine and Freshwater Research. 2010 Sep 23;61(9):963-70.</a></p>
<p>That’s all for now, but I’ll keep updating the list as a find new sources. Feel free to comment and add to this list also.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>research</category>
  <guid>https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2026-01-17-ecologists-reading-list-tassie-reefs/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jan 2026 13:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>I catch my own fish so my seafood is sustainable</title>
  <link>https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2026-01-16-is-my-rec-fishing-sustainable/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>“I catch my own fish, so it’s sustainable” is a claim I often hear from recreational fishers. But is that really true?</p>
<p>Fishing selectively and at a small-scale does not guarantee that fishing will be sustainable. In fact, a lot of recreational fisheries are in bad shape.</p>
<p>Let me explain why and what you can do about it.</p>
<p><img src="https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2026-01-16-is-my-rec-fishing-sustainable/people-fishing-of-a-dock.jpeg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<section id="what-does-sustainable-fishing-actually-mean" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-does-sustainable-fishing-actually-mean">What does ‘sustainable fishing’ actually mean?</h2>
<p>When we talk about sustainable fishing, we need to consider at least two different perspectives. First, there’s the species-level view: can the fish population you’re targeting persist through time at the current level of fishing pressure? If you’re removing fish faster than they can reproduce, the population will decline until it eventually collapses. This might happen slowly over decades or quickly within a few years, but the end result is the same.</p>
<p>But sustainability isn’t just about keeping fish populations above zero. Ideally our fisheries are sustainable AND productive. Productive means maintaining the population at a level where it can produce plenty of new fish. We want healthy, thriving populations that can support productive harvests indefinitely, not barely surviving populations with depressed catches.</p>
<p>The second perspective is ecosystem-level sustainability. Every fishing method has impacts beyond the species you’re targeting. These ecosystem effects come through several pathways, but the most obvious is bycatch - the fish and other animals you catch accidentally while trying to catch something else.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-ecosystem-impacts-of-recreational-fishing-are-often-small" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-ecosystem-impacts-of-recreational-fishing-are-often-small">The ecosystem impacts of recreational fishing are often small</h2>
<p>I think when people say their recreational fishing is ‘sustainable’ they are thinking about small-scale fishing methods that are pretty focused on catching just a few species, like hook and line. Then they are comparing these methods with industrial scale methods, like deep sea trawling which can catch tonnes of fish in a single haul and can have high bycatch rates.</p>
<p>Different fishing methods have dramatically different bycatch rates. If I’m hook-and-line fishing for myself, I might catch a few undersized fish or the occasional unwanted species, but most of what comes up is what I was trying to catch.</p>
<p>But if I’m using nets, even recreationally, my bycatch can be substantial. Nets don’t discriminate. They catch everything that swims into them, including undersized fish, protected species, even turtles, dolphins, or seals. While your fishing might be sustainable for the species you’re targeting, it can be devastating for everything else.</p>
<p>The handling of released fish matters too. When you catch something undersized or out of season and throw it back, that fish might not survive. Some species survive well if caught and released. Others don’t. Chinook salmon in British Columbia, for instance, often die after release if they’re not handled carefully. The difference between a skilled angler who keeps the fish in the water and uses proper release techniques versus someone who dumps it on the deck can be the difference between survival and death for the fish (see the end of this post for further tips on handling).</p>
<p>A lot of recreational fishers catching and releasing fish that die can add up to a big issue for the fish population.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-death-by-a-thousand-cuts-problem" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-death-by-a-thousand-cuts-problem">The death by a thousand cuts problem</h2>
<p>Here’s where the “I only catch a few fish” argument breaks down. Your individual impact might seem negligible, but you’re not fishing alone. Thousands of other recreational fishers are targeting the same species. Collectively, recreational fishing pressure can match or even exceed commercial fishing pressure for some species.</p>
<p>Catches of sand flathead, a popular species where I live, are close to 100% recreational. So its poor outlook is done to too much recreational fishing.</p>
<p>Too many people fishing creates what scientists call the “tragedy of the commons.” Each individual fisher acts rationally from their perspective - they only take what they need, they follow the rules, they don’t see their personal impact as significant. But when everyone acts this way simultaneously, the combined pressure becomes unsustainable.</p>
<p>This has happened to recreational fisheries in many places all over the world.</p>
<p>The sand flathead, for instance, was a staple when I was a child, but now its classified by government as overfished and its much harder to catch a decent sized one (about 1/100 fish is of legal size near to where I live!).</p>
</section>
<section id="the-management-challenge" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-management-challenge">The management challenge</h2>
<p>The large numbers of participants mean that recreational fisheries are inherently difficult to manage.</p>
<p>The best managed commercial fisheries typically have a relatively small number of participants whose livelihoods depend on maintaining the resource. They have strong incentives to support sustainable management, even when it means short-term sacrifices. This is certaintly not true of all commercial fisheries, but there are many examples of where commercial fisheries are managed sustainably.</p>
<p>Recreational fisheries, by contrast, typically involve large numbers of casually engaged users. Most recreational fishers don’t depend on fishing for income or food. This creates different incentives and makes collective action much harder.</p>
<p>The political scientist Eleanor Ostrom won a Nobel Prize for her work showing that sustainable resource management works best when resource users are actively involved in management decisions. Her research on forestry demonstrated that community collectives who co-manage resources with government agencies achieve better sustainability outcomes than top-down government management alone.</p>
<p>These ideas have been shown to also apply to fisheries.</p>
<p>Small fishing communities with strong social connections can develop and enforce sustainable practices through peer pressure, collective monitoring, and shared responsibility. But recreational fisheries often lack these social structures. Most recreational fishers don’t know many of their fellow anglers and don’t participate in management decisions.</p>
<p>They are likely to follow the rules government sets, but ultimately they mostly see resource stewardship as a government responsibility.</p>
<p>New rules have been brought in for Tasmania’s much loved flathead for instance. The rules were set by government based on the world-class fisheries science (by my colleagues).</p>
<p>The success of these rules at turning around the fate of the flathead now depends on how whether individual recreational fishers follow those rules of not.</p>
<p>Likewise, there are strict rules that limit fishing for Chinook salmon in Canada and require careful handling of accidentally caught salmon. Whether the Chinook can recover depends on whether people follow those rules.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-you-can-do-as-a-recreational-fisher" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-you-can-do-as-a-recreational-fisher">What you can do as a recreational fisher</h2>
<p>Ostrom’s work suggests that just following the rules as an individual isn’t enough. She showed that sustainability requires active participation by the community.</p>
<p>The first step as an individual is to learn and adopt best practices for whatever fishing method you use. Learn proper handling techniques for catch-and-release. Use gear that minimizes bycatch. Follow size and bag limits even when nobody’s watching. These individual actions matter, but they’re only part of the solution.</p>
<p>The next step is getting involved in the management of your fishery. Once you are educated you should be helping educate your peers as well.</p>
<p>The first time I was fishing in Canada, I had bought my fishing license and learnt the rules, but was otherwise a novice. But I very quickly realized the people on the shore around me knew even less.</p>
<p>I jumped in (in a friendly way) to help some young folks who were struggling to know how to handle their catch. It was an opportunity to show them proper handling techniques, how to identify and measure the fish they caught. Once it became apparent their catch was a keeper, I also helped them with preparation so they’d have high quality fillets (leaving a fish lying in the hot sun isn’t going to result in a good meal).</p>
<p>Educating peers, and a bit of peer pressure, was an important lesson from Ostrom’s work.</p>
<p>It is also important for recreational fishers to participate actively in management.</p>
<p>This could mean getting involved with scientific monitoring programs, attending public meetings about fishery management, and supporting sustainable management measures on when you post on social media.</p>
<p>Many regions have programs where recreational fishers can contribute to scientific data collection. You might return tagged fish, provide fish frames for scientific studies, or participate in catch surveys. These programs directly inform management decisions, but they only work if fishers participate.</p>
<p>You can also advocate for better management. Contact your local politician about supporting sustainable fisheries management. Support organizations that work on fishery conservation. Most importantly, help create a culture of stewardship within the recreational fishing community.</p>
</section>
<section id="taking-responsibility" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="taking-responsibility">Taking responsibility</h2>
<p>The assumption that recreational fishing is automatically sustainable because it’s small-scale and local doesn’t match ecological reality.</p>
<p>Sustainable recreational fishing requires the same elements as sustainable commercial fishing: good science, effective management, and responsible resource users. That might mean catching fewer fish in the short term. It definitely means getting more involved in management and stewardship.</p>
<p>The good news is that recreational fishers can be powerful advocates for conservation when they organize effectively. You have firsthand knowledge of local conditions, you spend time on the water that managers and scientists can’t match, and you have political influence as voters and taxpayers.</p>
<p>So next time someone tells you that recreational fishing is sustainable, ask them what they mean. Sustainability isn’t about the scale of your fishing or your motivations for doing it. It’s about whether your actions, combined with everyone else’s, maintain healthy fish populations and ecosystems over time. That requires active participation, not passive assumption.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>research</category>
  <guid>https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2026-01-16-is-my-rec-fishing-sustainable/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 13:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>LLMs can’t be trusted to do scientific coding accurately, but humans make mistakes too</title>
  <link>https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2026-01-14-LLMs-cant-be-trusted-but-neither-can-humans/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I often hear the comment that LLMs/generative AI (large language models) can’t be trusted for research tasks.</p>
<p><img src="https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2026-01-14-LLMs-cant-be-trusted-but-neither-can-humans/aislop.jpeg" class="img-fluid"> <strong>Image</strong> Google’s Nano Banana tasked with “Generate an image of a male African researcher holding a balloon that is pulling them up above a tidal wave of AI generated slop that is full of errors. The balloon has a research paper inside of it. Generate the image in the style of a Simpsons cartoon.”</p>
<p>But this is the wrong way to think about LLMs. <strong>Humans also can’t be trusted</strong> to do scientific research accurately. They make mistakes. That’s why we have systems for review.</p>
<p>The more important question is: Are LLMs more accurate than humans at completing a given task?</p>
<p>I actually think LLMs might lead to better scientific coding and statistical analysis.</p>
<p>A common example of what LLMs get criticised for is writing code or performing statistical analyses. The LLM might hallucinate non-truths, or at least mislead you into thinking the analysis you have done is scientifically accurate.</p>
<p>The implication is that we should not be using them for particular tasks, like designing statistical models.</p>
<p>Its right to be skeptical of AI produced output. However, we also need to be skeptical of human produced output. Humans make mistakes as well.</p>
<p>As scientists peer-review is baked into our culture. But code review is much rarer. We also don’t have many systematic reviews of scientific coding that have quantified the rate of mistakes.</p>
<p>I suspect that mistakes in scientific coding are more common than we’d like to believe.</p>
<p>In one (rare) example, <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0304380019301085">researchers reviewed population modelling analyses and found mathematical errors were common</a>. One type of error occured in 62% of studies!</p>
<p>Now I haven’t set an LLM agent the task of doing the equivalent population models to see what its error rate is. However, my tests (which are under review) of agents at quite complicated stats and ecological modelling are showing 80-90% performance at accurately completing the tasks.</p>
<p>So the LLM agents are potentially doing better than the humans and making fewer mistakes.</p>
<p>Why I think LLMs might lead to better research is that they give us more time for code review.</p>
<p>As an ecological modeller I invest a ton of time into writing code, then checking that code works the way I want (and in a mathematically accurate way).</p>
<p>LLMs are now doing more of the code writing for me. Used effectively, this gives me more time to review the code for accuracy, as well as checking the code is an accurate representation of the scientific theory.</p>
<p>A human with an LLM partner could choose to: (1) produce crap work faster than pre-LLM, OR (2) produce higher quality work in a similar amount of time to what it took them pre-LLM.</p>
<p>I’m arguing that we should be aiming to produce the higher quality work. We can do this if we use LLMs to speed up code, then use the extra time for more quality assurance.</p>
<p>More generally, don’t get fooled by the argument that “genAI makes mistakes, so it can’t be trusted”.</p>
<p>Its the wrong way to think about the problem, and I think will lead us to being blind-sided by the oncoming flood of research slop created with genAI.</p>
<p>A better way to think about it is: “genAI and humans both make mistakes, how can we design workflows so that their strengths complement each other and we produce higher quality work”.</p>
<p>This will give us outcomes that are of higher quality than the pre-LLM world, and hopefully will rise above the huge quantity of AI generated slop that is currently happening.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>rstats</category>
  <category>genAI</category>
  <guid>https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2026-01-14-LLMs-cant-be-trusted-but-neither-can-humans/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 13:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Saving ocean animals means restoring multiple habitats at the same time</title>
  <link>https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2026-01-04-marine-seascape-restoration/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The sub-tidal (underwater) habitats of our coasts are rarely uniform. They are often mosiacs of many different types of habitats, and that’s the way animals like it.</p>
<p>For instance, the Great Barrier Reef is famous for being a living organism you can see from space. But there is a lot more to the reef than coral reefs. The reef ecosystem is an enormous mosaic of corals, sand, seagrass, sponges, mangroves and many other habitat habitats.</p>
<p>In fact, the area of seagrass meadows - which is just what it sounds like, underwater grass - in the Great Barrier Reef is greater than its area of coral reefs.</p>
<p>Many other coastal habitats are similarly patchy. Kelp forests are bordered by sand and seagrass, mangroves are interconnected with saltmarshes and coral reefs and seagrass is often patchy meadows interspersed by sand, rather than a continuous block.</p>
<p>Mosaics of habitats are like shops around a village town square. A village with just lolly shops would suit my children, but not many others. A village with cafes, flower shops, gift stores, stationary stores and others would draw in lots of different customers.</p>
<p>Similarly, diverse coastal habitat arrangements tend to support a greater diversity of animals than uniform blocks.</p>
<p>As animals move around these networks of habitats they also help make connections among them.</p>
<p><img src="https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2026-01-04-marine-seascape-restoration/seagrass-giantkelp1.jpeg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><strong>Image:</strong> Boundaries of different habitats, here a giant kelp grows next to a seagrass meadow near my home in Tasmania, are often popular with ocean animals. Photo by Chris Brown.</p>
<p>There are numerous examples. For example, one species of fish that rests on coral reefs during the day, swims to nearby areas to feed at night. In doing so, they transport nutrients (in the form of fish wee and poo) to areas nearby the reefs, benefiting other organisms.</p>
<section id="denmarks-coastal-habitat-mosaics" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="denmarks-coastal-habitat-mosaics">Denmark’s coastal habitat mosaics</h2>
<p>We are getting much better at successfully restoring some coastal habitats and seeing some great wins for ocean animals. But for this to really work for animals we need to restore mosaics of habitats, not just one habitat at time.</p>
<p>That’s why what they’ve done with habitat restoration in Denmark is really unique.</p>
<p>In Vejle Fjord government and scientists have been working together to restore seagrass, boulder reefs and mussel beds since 2019. Historically these habitats were abundant. But agricultural run-off and extraction of boulders has converted the system to one dominated by muddy sand (soft sediments).</p>
<p>To date, the restoration of the three habitats is extensive, about 22 football (soccer) fields worth of habitat.</p>
<p>This is a large area compared to your typical coastal restoration project. But, what is unique here is the restoration of multiple habitats in the same area.</p>
<p><img src="https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2026-01-04-marine-seascape-restoration/vejle-ford-restoration.jpeg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p><strong>Image</strong> Map of the restoration site showing the different habitats that have been restored from <a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/eap.70163">Sievers et al.&nbsp;2025</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="studying-the-how-restoration-of-seascapes-benefits-animals" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="studying-the-how-restoration-of-seascapes-benefits-animals">Studying the how restoration of seascapes benefits animals</h2>
<p>The mosiac of restoration sites created the opportunity to study how animals would respond to the new seascape.</p>
<p>My colleague, Michael Sievers, worked with the Danish restoration science tea to count fish, prawns and sea snails in the seagrass and nearby bare sediment. Their surveys of animals included areas of remaining natural seagrass, as well as seagrass that had been planted in the restoration efforts.</p>
<p>When Michael invited me to help with the data analysis I jumped at the chance. I specialize in statistics and data analysis, and the way the surveys were done here meant there was potential to ask some really interesting questions about restoration ecology.</p>
<p>Michael wanted to know how if the animals did better when seagrass restoration was near to the mussel and boulder reefs that had also been restored.</p>
<p>The surveys were done in restored seagrass at different distances from the boulder and mussel reefs. This meant we could use the statistics to see if seagrass restored close to boulder or mussel reefs was better for the animals that might move among those habitats.</p>
<p>So I built a models of how animal numbers in a single location changed with the amount of seagrass and the distance to the other habitats. The model is a mathematical equation that describes a relationship like ‘as seagrass area increase we see more baltic prawns’.</p>
<p>The equation is built using statistics and the data, so it represents the real trends in the data. That’s why the survey design with different distances to different habitats was key. The model only works if it can find trends in the data.</p>
<p>The seagrass meadows were also patchy, some were larger than others. So we could also use the data to ask if larger areas of seagrass were better for animals when compared to mosaics of seagrass and soft sediment.</p>
<p>We found seagrass specialist species, like periwinkles, preferred larger areas of seagrass close to mussel reefs. Other species, like juvenile flatfish, preferred soft sediment that was near to mussel reefs, so there were fewer of them at the seagrass restoration sites.</p>
<p>Finally, some species preferred mosaics. Pipefish, which are a like a long thin seahorse, preferred patchy mosiacs of seagrass and soft sediment.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-if-we-did-restoration-differently" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-if-we-did-restoration-differently">‘What if’ we did restoration differently</h2>
<p>The models let us ask ‘what if’ questions about different ways to arrange the restoration of coastal habitats.</p>
<p>We calculated how many animals there would be with different seagrass plantings. For instance, what if the seagrass was planted only near to boulder reefs? What if it was planted far away from boulder reefs? What if it was planted in a mosaic of patches?</p>
<p>We found the best arrangements were different for each type of animal. The seagrass specialists liked a lot of seagrass planted in patches with small areas of soft sediment between it, like a checkerboard.</p>
<p>The species caught by fisheries (brown shrimp and flatfish) did best with large patches of seagrass and large patches of soft sediment.</p>
<p>Our study shows there are benefits to restoring whole seascapes of habitats together. Going forward I hope it can provide a pathway and motivation for other places to tackle the challenge of restoring seascapes.</p>
</section>
<section id="further-reading" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="further-reading">Further reading</h2>
<p>Michael’s study on animals at the Denmark restoration site https://doi.org/10.1002/eap.70163</p>
<p>Great Barrier Reef habitats https://www2.gbrmpa.gov.au/learn/fascinating-facts-about-great-barrier-reef</p>
<p>Seagrass on the reef https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0272771414002078</p>
<p>Linkages among coastal habitats https://www.nature.com/articles/s44183-024-00095-1</p>
<p>Example of connections: Benefits of fish poo for nearby ecosystems https://esajournals.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1002/ecs2.2225</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>research</category>
  <guid>https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2026-01-04-marine-seascape-restoration/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 03 Jan 2026 13:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Rethinking ecological predictions and uncertainty</title>
  <link>https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2025-12-16-rethinking-ecological-predictions-and-uncertainty/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Ecological modelling is a science geared towards predicting change in ecosystems. But I think for many ecosystems we’ve been going about making predictions the wrong way. We are overlooking how slight changes in feedbacks within ecosystems can lead to runaway outcomes far beyond what we anticipated.</p>
<p>Consequently, we have too much confidence in our ability to build models that predict well.</p>
<p>An alternative way to predict change is to acknowledge and then try to represent high levels of uncertainty in ecological feedback processes. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/gcb.70468">Qualitative models are one way to do this</a>.</p>
<section id="types-of-ecological-models" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="types-of-ecological-models">Types of ecological models</h2>
<p>Increasingly sophisticated models of ecological mechanisms are being used to make predictions ecological change and support challenging management problems like climate change.</p>
<p>One example are the global forest models that are used to predict carbon sequestration from the atmosphere by the world’s forests for the next 50-100 years. Predicting carbon sequestration is essential as it is one part of estimating future atmospheric carbon dioxide, an essential component of the global climate models that predict how much our world will warm.</p>
<p>Statistical models and machine learning are also key areas of innovation. These models tend to focus on describing patterns, over mechanistic detail of the model formulation (though there are exceptions of course). Much effort is invested in developing models that make use of data to capture multiple sources of uncertainty and describe non-linear relationships.</p>
<p>A leading example are the species distribution models that predict where species occur in space. This information is essential for a range of applications, including protected area design, threatened species management and managing species responses to climate change.</p>
<p>What the statistical models that focus on patterns and the mechanistic models share in common is a focus on quantitative predictions. That is, making precise predictions of how much - how much forest, how much carbon, probability of species occurrence and how many species.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-were-missing" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-were-missing">What we’re missing</h2>
<p>The focus on quantitative predictions puts a lot of faith in our ability to build useful models. For mechanistic models the faith is that we have enough knowledge to know which equations are important. For the statistical and machine learning models the faith is that the data can reveal the important insights.</p>
<p>But what if uncertainty about ecological futures is much greater than we ecologists typically acknowledge?</p>
<p>One example is that marine scientists were totally blindsided by <a href="https://theconversation.com/like-an-underwater-bushfire-sas-marine-algal-bloom-is-still-killing-almost-everything-in-its-path-257885">this unprecedented algal bloom</a> that caused people to get sick and killed wildlife along 100s kilometres of coastline. Scientists still don’t know what triggered it.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-importance-of-feedback-processes" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-importance-of-feedback-processes">The importance of feedback processes</h2>
<p>Run-away feedback processes often feature in unanticapted ecological change. The algal bloom initiated a run-away feedback process kind of like a zombie plague. It was killing animals and plant life, the decomposition then created more nutrients that further fueled the bloom.</p>
<div class="cell" data-layout-align="default">
<div class="cell-output-display">
<div>
<p></p><figure class="figure"><p></p>
<div>
<pre class="mermaid mermaid-js">flowchart LR
  A[Algal bloom] --&gt; B[Death of animals and plants]
  B --&gt; C[Decomposition]
  C --&gt; D[Increased nutrients]
  D --&gt; A
</pre>
</div>
<p></p></figure><p></p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Slight changes in these types of feedbacks can result in drastically divergent futures. Representing different plausible feedbacks and different weights for those feedbacks therefore is one way to get at estimating the range of outcomes for the future.</p>
</section>
<section id="qualitative-loop-models" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="qualitative-loop-models">Qualitative loop models</h2>
<p>Loop models are models of feedbacks interconnected systems. They have also been called network models.</p>
<p>Loop models have nodes, which can represent physical or ecological entities such as nutrient concentration, species population size or forest area, and connections, which represent the feedbacks among nodes. Critically, they <em>qualitative</em> predictions of change in the nodes in response to change in other nodes. That is, if one node was to increase will the other nodes increase, stay the same or decrease?</p>
<p>Qualitative models can be <a href="https://esajournals.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1890/12-0207.1?casa_token=nr7e7AeLDawAAAAA%3AAoJqWz-qsoV8ywDuzvVWl_hhbooGJJtHdF0YWTHxNboQnW4yFYQCrjQ7UhppD1Hf5Ts2ICvaRfHdipNa">extended to model the probability of a positive or negative change</a>. They do this by simulating different weights for the feedback loops, across a distribution of plausible weights.</p>
<p>This creates the possibility of exploring how different feedback processes affect the probability of future increases or decreases in an ecosystem.</p>
</section>
<section id="application-of-qualitative-models-to-a-high-uncertainty-situation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="application-of-qualitative-models-to-a-high-uncertainty-situation">Application of qualitative models to a high uncertainty situation</h2>
<p>Rising seas and coastal development are pushing mangrove forests beyond their historical limits. Predicting how mangroves will respond is much harder when environmental change is unprecedented. In our study, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/gcb.70468">Projecting Uncertainty in Ecosystem Persistence Under Climate Change</a>, we aimed to estimate the probability that mangrove forests will persist or decline worldwide.</p>
<p>Previous global studies predicting mangrove change have used mechanistic models that make precise quantitative predictions. But I think these models are not honest to the amount of uncertainty we have about mangrove forest dynamics. And the mechanistic models have been criticised for not representing important feedbacks between mangroves and the soils and sediment they grow on.</p>
<p>We used qualitative models to represent feedback processes in mangrove forests.</p>
<p>A mangrove that is healthy traps sediment in its root structures. This sediment helps it rise-up out of the water slowly over time, which is key to persistence if sea levels are rising.</p>
<p><img src="https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2025-12-16-rethinking-ecological-predictions-and-uncertainty/mangrove-feedback-loop.jpeg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Image: Chris Brown with Gemini Pro 3.</p>
<p>But if sediment supplies are cut-off, such as by building a dam upstream, the mangrove can no longer capture sediment to keep up with sea-level-rise. Eventually, the mangrove will be drowned and disappear.</p>
<div class="cell" data-layout-align="default">
<div class="cell-output-display">
<div>
<p></p><figure class="figure"><p></p>
<div>
<pre class="mermaid mermaid-js">flowchart LR
  A[Healthy mangrove] --&gt; B[Sediment trapping]
  B --&gt; C[Elevation gain]
  C --&gt; D[Persistence with sea-level rise]
  D --&gt; A
  E[Reduced sediment supply] -.-&gt; |Breaks feedback| B
  E --&gt; F[Drowning]
</pre>
</div>
<p></p></figure><p></p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>We mapped the loop models to global data on the distribution of mangroves and their threats to make predictions across the world’s mangroves. Those predictions were made under climate scenario modelling so we could account for multiple climate threats.</p>
<p>Here’s the projections for persistence of mangroves from one of our scenarios:</p>
<p><img src="https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2025-12-16-rethinking-ecological-predictions-and-uncertainty/Buelow_etal2025-graphical-abstract.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>We didn’t stop at predicting the future, we also made hindcasts. This let us validate the model against observations, to get an idea of how certain the model was.</p>
<p>For the future predictions, rising seas, storms and reduced sediment from dammed rivers create multiple pressures that led to predicted mangrove loss. In contrast, about 30% of forests were predicted to gain area landward, as they move inland with sea-level rise. However, coastal development often blocks this migration.</p>
<p>Perhaps most importantly, uncertainty is high. In more than half the mangrove units studied, we couldn’t predict whether forests would persist or decline - the probability was essentially random.</p>
</section>
<section id="applications-to-management-and-conservation-of-ecosystems" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="applications-to-management-and-conservation-of-ecosystems">Applications to management and conservation of ecosystems</h2>
<p>Useful predictions don’t have to be accurate. It can be more helpful to know what you don’t know. This means acknowledging the uncertainty in the system you are trying to model.</p>
<p>We tested conservation scenarios and found encouraging results. With targeted management - sediment addition, barrier removal, and assisted migration - the number of units likely to persist could nearly double.</p>
<p>Learning where we don’t know enough to make useful predictions is also useful. This isn’t a model failure. It tells us where better data could tip the balance.</p>
<p>Embracing modelling of feedbacks means embracing uncertainty in ecological futures. Doing so will make our predictions more honest and ultimately more useful for management.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>research</category>
  <category>modelling</category>
  <category>coastal-wetlands</category>
  <guid>https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2025-12-16-rethinking-ecological-predictions-and-uncertainty/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 13:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Should we still teach R coding in this age of genAI?</title>
  <link>https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2025-12-10-should-we-teach-coding/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I often get asked if we should still be teaching coding skills to students and researchers now that we have generative AI tools that can write code for us.</p>
<p>The general consensus is yes, we should still teach coding. For an ecology specific <a href="https://besjournals.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1111/2041-210X.14325">argument see here</a>.</p>
<p>Teaching coding is teaching people how to think logically and structure problems. These skills are essential not only in coding, but also for good science and problem solving in general.</p>
<p>So you need to learn to code to learn to think logically and structure problems.</p>
<p>A more practical standpoint is that LLMs are good at generating code that they have seen a lot of examples of in their data. But they are not so good at creative work on novel topics or niche areas.</p>
<p>For example, AI coding assistants struggle to make a simple <code>tmap</code> (the R mapping package) work well. <code>tmap</code> was updated recently, meaning the examples in the LLM’s training are out of date.</p>
<p>The coding assistants also seem to default to code patterns they are most familiar with, like <code>ggplot2</code> syntax. Not all of this works with <code>tmap</code>.</p>
<p>In general, I find they perform much better at statistical modelling in R than they do with complex geospatial analyses.</p>
<p>This practical issue may increasingly become less relevant as LLMs get better and we create better resources to inform their actions (like a tmap specific guide for LLMs to read before advising you, or web searches of the tmap page).</p>
<p>But it is still likely that frontier modelling will require deep human engagement with code. So learning to code is important for researchers.</p>
<p>I’ll leave the final say to Andrej Karpathy, former head of AI at Tesla and founding member of OpenAI’s research group.</p>
<p>In a <a href="https://www.dwarkesh.com/p/andrej-karpathy">recent podcast interview</a> he talks about a repo he made to help teach people how to work with LLMs. His advice to learners is literally to re-write his repo by hand, not even to cut and paste.</p>
<p>He goes on to explain that AI agents are good for very standard code or code that is common on the internet. But they perform poorly for creating new code, or code that contradicts common patterns.</p>
<p>For any research code he most commonly uses the code auto-complete features that AI assistants have, rather than AI agents.</p>
<p>He suggests that to really learn something you should code it yourself, using examples only as references.</p>
<p>Karpathy came up with the term ‘vibe-coding’ which means creating code by prompting, without reviewing the code. Usually an AI agent is used. So its saying a lot if he thinks that learning means doing it the old fashioned way of writing code yourself.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>rstats</category>
  <category>genAI</category>
  <guid>https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2025-12-10-should-we-teach-coding/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 13:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>How AI coding assistants can bias your coding and analysis</title>
  <link>https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2025-12-09-biasing-when-using-AI-coding-assistants/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I’m a frequent user of AI coding assistants to speed up my coding. I’m mostly using Github Copilot and the Roo Code agentic extension for VSCode, with various large language models (LLMs).</p>
<p>We hear a lot about biases and LLMs, which got me wondering, what biases might the use of coding assistants induce in my coding and data analysis?</p>
<p>Biases are a concern in other areas of applications of LLMs to the workplace. For instance, LLMs are known to be sexist, biased towards recommending science articles from certain parts of the world and even biased towards <a href="https://futurism.com/grok-looks-up-what-elon-musk-thinks">Elon Musk’s opinions</a>.</p>
<p>I had thought that using LLMs mainly to assist with R code would mean that I’m reasonably immune to issues with biases in LLMs.</p>
<p>But after a recent experience in Python I realized there are subtle types of biases in LLMs that could have a big impact on the quality of an analysis.</p>
<p>I had considered that LLMs might recommend certain types of statistical tests more frequently than others, perhaps biasing me to the dominant statistical methodologies (like they seem to more commonly recommend frequentist over Bayesian generalized linear models).</p>
<p>But I wasn’t concerned about that. I have a pretty broad view of stats in my field, and I usually don’t use LLMs for recommending new methods. I look to the scientific literature for that advice.</p>
<p>LLMs might have their own particular ways of implementing code, but the end result of a given statistical test, is the same, it doesn’t matter much how you get there.</p>
<p>Using Python changed my view on this. I’m a lifelong R coder, not a Python coder. However, I wanted to learn some deep learning analyses, for which I needed Python. So I set about using my coding assistant to write me a tutorial on learn deep learning in Python.</p>
<p>The way LLM coding assistants can bias your code is that most are set-up to be sycophantic. So they amplify your own biases by affirming that whatever you have is good.</p>
<p>This became apparent when me, the R coder, was bringing my R informed ideas for writing code to Python. The LLM led me down paths for implementing code that make sense in R land, but which are not best practice for implementation in Python.</p>
<p>I realized this once I started referring to real Python tutorials.</p>
<p>More generally, LLMs tend to be affirmative of your requests. For a data analysis workflow this means they will tend to amplify whatever biases you start out with.</p>
<p>Errors that cause code to fail are ok, because they are easy to detect. What is more concerning is if the LLM amplify subtle mistakes in choice of statistics.</p>
<p>I have a <a href="https://ecoevorxiv.org/repository/view/9493/">pre-print on using LLMs and AI coding assistants for ecological data analysis</a>. One of our recommendations is to split your workflow into parts.</p>
<p>In particular, it helps to choose the analysis before you plan how the code will be written (and what software or packages you will use). If you conflate these two different decisions you are more likely to make mistakes that are amplified. Best to choose your analysis using AI but also by reading the literature. Then get the AI to help you implement that.</p>
<p>The other problem is that you finish your analysis and the LLM has led you to think it is excellent. You submit that analysis for peer-review and the reviewers think differently.</p>
<p>So its a good idea to check your work against the discipline norms, and ideally get expert colleagues to take a look too. Take everything an LLM says with a grain of salt, especially if it agrees with you.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>rstats</category>
  <category>genAI</category>
  <guid>https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2025-12-09-biasing-when-using-AI-coding-assistants/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 13:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Giant kelp restoration could boost fisheries productivity in Tasmania</title>
  <link>https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2025-12-08-kelp-restoration-fisheries/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Kelp restoration is gaining <a href="https://kelpforestalliance.com/">global momentum</a> with recognition that we are losing kelp forests and the values they provide as habitat for biodiversity and supporting fisheries.</p>
<p>But questions remain. We wanted to know if restoring giant kelp forests boost productivity for commercially important species like abalone and rock lobster. We <a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/aqc.70242">explore this question in our new study</a>. (Free access version <a href="https://www.biorxiv.org/content/biorxiv/early/2024/12/20/2024.12.16.628810.full.pdf">here</a> or <a href="mailto:c.j.brown@utas.edu.au">email me</a> for a copy)</p>
<p>We took measurements of kelp growth from Tasmania’s East Coast and used them in models of ecosystems to study how gain kelp restoration could impact fisheries.</p>
<p>We found the productivity gains could be substantial.</p>
<p><img src="https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2025-12-08-kelp-restoration-fisheries/kelp-productvity-foodwebs.jpg" class="img-fluid"> <strong>Figure</strong> Key findings</p>
<section id="why-giant-kelp-matters" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-giant-kelp-matters">Why giant kelp matters</h2>
<p>Giant kelp <em>Macrocystis pyrifera</em> has largely disappeared from Tasmania’s east coast, replaced by the less productive <em>Ecklonia radiata</em>. The productivity difference between these two species is striking - giant kelp is approximately 40 times more productive than Ecklonia.</p>
<p>That extra productivity has to go somewhere. While we still need more research to fully understand the fate of giant kelp biomass, the evidence suggests it flows through the food web to support a wide range of species, including those important for fisheries.</p>
</section>
<section id="modelling-food-web-effects" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="modelling-food-web-effects">Modelling food web effects</h2>
<p>We used ecosystem models to trace how increased macroalgae productivity from giant kelp restoration moves through the food web. The model shows productivity flowing from the restored kelp to herbivores like abalone, then up through different predator-prey interactions to boost productivity across many species in the ecosystem.</p>
<p>The most confident results come from the productivity measurements themselves - based on extensive, long-term datasets comparing giant kelp and Ecklonia across different areas and seasons.</p>
<p>Then we use those data in the model to predict the effects of meeting Australia’s restoration targets for giant kelp (restore 30% of degraded habitats).</p>
<p>The model predicted improvements of fishery catch of 1-7%, depending on the species. This is a substantial improvement given the scale of the model is the entirety of Tasmania and the area of kelp restoration is relatively small compared to that total area.</p>
<p><img src="https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2025-12-08-kelp-restoration-fisheries/2023-11-13_kelp-forest.jpg" class="img-fluid"> <strong>Figure</strong> Giant kelp breaking up in later summer - its death and decomposition provides food to microbes that feeds energy into the local foodweb.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-the-models-dont-capture" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-the-models-dont-capture">What the models don’t capture</h2>
<p>Our model looked across all of Tasmania’s waters. Future improvements could study local changes in fishery productivity near to kelp forests. These are likely to be more substantial and could benefit fishers the most in those areas.</p>
<p>The models focused on overall ecosystem productivity gains, but giant kelp provides additional benefits not captured in these predictions. Restoring dense surface canopies creates more habitat and refuge for juvenile fish, which could lead to even higher increases in fish productivity than the models predict.</p>
</section>
<section id="from-global-goals-to-local-action" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="from-global-goals-to-local-action">From global goals to local action</h2>
<p>Our study demonstrates how global restoration targets can be translated into specific, outcome-based goals relevant to local communities. In Tasmania, the positive impacts of giant kelp restoration on kelp forest health and fisheries productivity align well with local values and needs.</p>
<p>Models are particularly valuable at this stage of kelp restoration because we’re still in the early phases of upscaling. In the absence of previous large-scale examples to learn from, models help set realistic expectations and make the case for restoration investments. Models like this help show how restoration has relevance to communities. Community groups are more likely to support restoration when expected outcomes are clear and relevant to their specific needs.</p>
<p>Giant kelp is worth restoring not just because it’s something we’ve lost, but because of the ecosystem-wide benefits it provides.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>research</category>
  <guid>https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2025-12-08-kelp-restoration-fisheries/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2025 13:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>New report looks at how we allocate monitoring of fishing activities</title>
  <link>https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2025-12-02-how-to-allocate-fisheries-monitoring/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>How do we monitor fisheries to know if seafood is sustainable? It turns out WHERE we monitor is just as important as HOW MUCH we monitor. The “where” needs to be codified in fisheries policies if we want a reliable picture of what is caught.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.nature.org/content/dam/tnc/nature/en/documents/t/n/TNC-Utas-2025-estimatingCatch.pdf">In this new report with The Nature Conservancy</a> we explore the implications of different ways of monitoring a fishery, especially with modern electronic monitoring (video) tech. The problem is that current policies might say “Monitor 30% of fishing activity”, but they are not specific about how that 30% is allocated.</p>
<p><img src="https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2025-12-02-how-to-allocate-fisheries-monitoring/Figure1conceptual.jpg" class="img-fluid"> <strong>Figure</strong> Different monitoring protocols, we recommend monitoring all vessels and then sub-sampling your 30% randomly, to get an unbiased estimate of catch and bycatch.</p>
<p>The most reliable data is provided when you have cameras on every vessel, then sample those videos at random. But ‘monitor 30%’ could also be interpreted as 30% of vessels or 30% of fishing trips. The 30% you see might be the best 30% and you miss high bycatch of threatened species in the other 70%, for instance.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.nature.org/content/dam/tnc/nature/en/documents/t/n/TNC-Utas-2025-estimatingCatch.pdf">Read the report</a> to learn more.</p>
<p>It was great to work with Vienna Saccomanno and Ben Gilmer from TNC on this question, which comes down to using ecological statistics to solve a real policy issue.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>research</category>
  <guid>https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2025-12-02-how-to-allocate-fisheries-monitoring/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 13:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>AI has raised the bar for literature reviews</title>
  <link>https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2025-12-01-ai-raises-bar-literature-reviews/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I’ve been reviewing papers recently that provide lists of applications - particularly common in reviews about AI use in ecology and fisheries. But lists of topics don’t provide a compelling read.</p>
<p>More importantly, any chatbot can generate a well researched list now. ChatGPT, Claude, and Copilot all have web search integrated. <a href="https://www.seascapemodels.org/AI-assistants-for-scientific-coding/10-research-applications-LLMs.html#sec-websearch">Perplexity AI</a> can generate detailed accurately referenced 10,000 word reports that are essentially lists on everything about a topic. Try asking “how can AI be used in ecology with references?” and you’ll get a comprehensive list in seconds.</p>
<p>If readers can generate that content themselves with AI, why would they bother reading your journal article? And if you’re producing content that AI can replicate, why does science need your career?</p>
<p>Generative AI raises the standard for what needs to go into literature reviews. Reviews need to be informed by deep human thought. AI can be a tool to help develop a review, but you need original insights that go beyond what everyday chatbots can produce.</p>
<p>One example that gets this right is <a href="https://besjournals.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/2041-210X.70120">a recent paper reviewing multimodal large language models in Methods in Ecology and Evolution</a>. They do list different applications of the technology, but there’s greater depth in the examples than what you could get out of an AI. They provide ecology-specific examples that take work to develop and find. More importantly, they synthesize these potential uses and discuss future challenges and directions with tangible actions.</p>
<p>Going forward, AI has raised the bar for literature reviews. Don’t write or produce anything that AI can easily generate. There’s no point - anyone can grab that content themselves and you are making yourself redundant. Reviews need to bring deep domain expertise, synthesis, and original thought.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>research-skills</category>
  <category>genAI</category>
  <guid>https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2025-12-01-ai-raises-bar-literature-reviews/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 13:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Tips on making science infographics with AI and nano banana</title>
  <link>https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2025-11-28-tips-making-infographics-with-ai/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I’ve been playing around with <a href="https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2025-11-23-exploring-gemini-3-image-generation/">Google Gemini Pro 3 (AKA Nano Banana)</a> as a way to make science infographics. Here are the key lessons from my attempts.</p>
<p>I’m accessing the model via API calls with Python, example code is at the end. However, you could also do this via the chat interface.</p>
<p>For the record I’d still prefer to work with a human to create great infographics. A good designed will give you much more than just create the image, they will help you think through the key points and how most accurately to represent those. You’ll see below that I had some issues with scientific accuracy of the AI generated images. But I don’t have the budget for a designer on every project. AI images are good if you are clear on the key points you want to communicate.</p>
<section id="be-clear-on-the-key-points-of-your-study" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="be-clear-on-the-key-points-of-your-study">Be clear on the key points of your study</h2>
<p>Like any science communication its important to be clear on the key points that you want to communicate from the outset. Then tell the those key points in your prompt.</p>
<p>But, another approach is…</p>
</section>
<section id="see-what-the-ai-comes-up-with" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="see-what-the-ai-comes-up-with">See what the AI comes up with</h2>
<p>Just point the AI to your study using a web search. It is pretty good at simultaneously interpreting the key points from the abstract and then generated an image to go along with that. Here’s my first attempt:</p>
<pre><code>Create a two panel infographic in cartoon style showing fisheries species that benefit from giant kelp restoration. In the left panel show small Ecklonia plants. In the right panel show giant kelp. Base the infographic on the recent study 'Predicting the impact of giant kelp restoration on food webs and fisheries production'. Include the 40x productivity boost. But don't include the numbers for the fishery species, just show which ones go up. Use bright colors and clear labels.</code></pre>
<p><img src="https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2025-11-28-tips-making-infographics-with-ai/study-cartoon-giant-kelp-restoration Large.jpeg" style="max-height: 600px; width: auto;"></p>
<p>With the web search feature enabled the model can find the article via the title I provided in the prompt.</p>
<p>This looks pretty nice for a very simple prompt and the ‘40x’ stat is accurate to the paper.</p>
<p>However on closer inspection there are a few issues.</p>
<p>The fish look North American, our study was in Tasmania. The abalone are upside down.</p>
<p>The biggest issue is that the image implies there was a 40X boost in productivity to fisheries, which is not what we found. <a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/aqc.70242">We found a 40x boost in kelp productivity that translated into 1-7% boost for fisheries</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="name-a-style" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="name-a-style">Name a style</h2>
<p>Its fun to play around with different styles. For the infographics below I tried ‘water colour style’ and ‘line-art botantical style’. You can get ideas for styles from lists on the web or a chatbot.</p>
<p>I don’t want the images to be too much like photos, I want it to be obvious that they are not ‘real’.</p>
<p>Some ideas for styles to mention:</p>
<ul>
<li>Cartoon (AI will choose its own style)</li>
<li>Watercolour</li>
<li>Botanical line-art</li>
<li>Like ‘The Simpsons’ or your favourite cartoon. Just add “Don’t include any proprietary characters in the image” to avoid it using images that might violate copyright.</li>
<li>Gothic</li>
<li>Pencil sketch</li>
<li>Manga</li>
</ul>
<p>Or anything that is common enough the AI will know it.</p>
</section>
<section id="include-reference-images" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="include-reference-images">Include reference images</h2>
<p>Next attempt I tried a water colour style and I attached reference images of Tasmanian reef fauna to the prompt:</p>
<pre><code>Create a two panel infographic in water colour style showing fisheries species that benefit from giant kelp restoration. In the left panel show a rocky reef with dense but small Ecklonia plants. In the right panel show a rocky reef with a healthy giant kelp forest. Include on the right panel the text: 40x kelp productivity boost. Include the animals in the reference images, showing more of them in the right panel. Redraw the animals to match the water colour style and so they look a natural part of the scene, but keep their essential morphological features intact. </code></pre>
<p><img src="https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2025-11-28-tips-making-infographics-with-ai/reef-scene2 Large.jpeg" style="max-height: 600px; width: auto;"></p>
<p>This looks more like a Tasmanian reef and is clearer that the 40x applies to kelp. But unfortunately the abalone are still upside down - I accidentally included an image of the abalone foot in my reference list.</p>
<p>The image also lacks context, so I wanted to try add some text in the watercolour style:</p>
<pre><code>Update this infographic to add a sub-panel to the left hand panel that reads: 'Giant kelp forests have disappeared in many places, but are more productive than other algae. O'Neill et al. used models to predict how giant kelp restoration can enhance fisheries'. Adjust the composition so all text is clearly readable and the images are arranged in a balanced, visually appealing layout.</code></pre>
<p>I also corrected the reference image for abalone to only show the shell.</p>
<p><img src="https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2025-11-28-tips-making-infographics-with-ai/reef-scene2d-gem3 Large.jpeg" style="max-height: 600px; width: auto;"></p>
<p>The coauthors and I were happy with this versio. I then just used powerpoint to add the DOI to the study as well as a statement: “Image: AI generated, human verified”.</p>
<p>I think people like to know what is generated by AI, but I wanted my audience to know that I had checked it for factual accuracy.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-more-text-the-more-likely-there-are-to-be-errors" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-more-text-the-more-likely-there-are-to-be-errors">The more text the more likely there are to be errors</h2>
<p>I had one more attempt with <a href="http://doi.org/10.1111/rec.70261">a study about mangrove restoration</a>.</p>
<p>For this one I had the prompt:</p>
<pre><code>Create an infographic in line-art botantical style explaining the following study for a general audience: ...</code></pre>
<p>Then I included the entire abstract in the prompt.</p>
<p><img src="https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2025-11-28-tips-making-infographics-with-ai/jordan-study-gem3 Large.jpeg" style="max-height: 600px; width: auto;"></p>
<p>If you look closely you will notice lots of errors in the text.</p>
</section>
<section id="prompting-with-the-study-abstract-didnt-work-as-well" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="prompting-with-the-study-abstract-didnt-work-as-well">Prompting with the study abstract didn’t work as well</h2>
<p>The infographic based on the abstract was also too detailed for what I wanted. It would be better to go back to tip 1 (be clear on study outcomes) and just provide the AI with 1-3 key points to represent.</p>
</section>
<section id="leave-space-for-post-production-modifications" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="leave-space-for-post-production-modifications">Leave space for post-production modifications</h2>
<p>I’d like to be able to modify these easily by adding text boxes in powerpoint (I’m not sophisticated with image editing!).</p>
<p>My final tip is to ask the AI to leave a ‘white box’ in a certain position, that way you can add text to it later, making sure it is accurate.</p>
</section>
<section id="example-python-code" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="example-python-code">Example python code</h2>
<p>See the <a href="https://ai.google.dev/gemini-api/docs/image-generation">Google API reference for image generation</a>.</p>
<p>Here’s the code I modified from there that uses reference images:</p>
<pre><code>from google import genai
from google.genai import types
import os
from PIL import Image

from dotenv import load_dotenv
load_dotenv()

api_key = os.getenv("GEMINI_API_KEY")


prompt = "Create a two panel infographic in water colour style showing fisheries species that benefit from giant kelp restoration. In the left panel show a rocky reef with dense but small Ecklonia plants. In the right panel show a rocky reef with a healthy giant kelp forest. Include on the right panel the text: 40x kelp productivity boost. Include the animals in the reference images, showing more of them in the right panel. Redraw the animals to match the water colour style and so they look a natural part of the scene, but keep their essential morphological features intact. "
aspect_ratio = "5:4" # "1:1","2:3","3:2","3:4","4:3","4:5","5:4","9:16","16:9","21:9"
resolution = "1K" # "1K", "2K", "4K"

client = genai.Client()

response = client.models.generate_content(
    model="gemini-3-pro-image-preview",
    contents=[
        prompt,
        Image.open('gemini-api/reef-images/abalone.png'),
        Image.open('gemini-api/reef-images/crab.png'),
        Image.open('gemini-api/reef-images/ecklonia.jpg'),
        Image.open('gemini-api/reef-images/lobster.png'),
        Image.open('gemini-api/reef-images/trumpeter.png'),
        Image.open('gemini-api/reef-images/wrasse.png')
    ],
    config=types.GenerateContentConfig(
        response_modalities=['TEXT', 'IMAGE'],
        image_config=types.ImageConfig(
            aspect_ratio=aspect_ratio,
            image_size=resolution
        ),
    )
)

for part in response.parts:
    if part.text is not None:
        print(part.text)
    elif image:= part.as_image():
        image.save("gemini-api/reef-images/reef-scene3.png")

</code></pre>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>research</category>
  <category>genAI</category>
  <guid>https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2025-11-28-tips-making-infographics-with-ai/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 13:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Reasoning and infographics with Nano Banana</title>
  <link>https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2025-11-23-exploring-gemini-3-image-generation/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The new Google Gemini Pro 3 (AKA Nano Banana) has some <a href="https://minimaxir.com/2025/11/nano-banana-prompts/">pretty impressive image generation capabilities</a>. It is very accurate to what you ask in the prompt, it can ‘ground’ image generation with web searches and it accurately renders text (most of the time). This increases its usefulness for scientific visualisation purposes over previous models.</p>
<p>Read more about <a href="https://ai.google.dev/gemini-api/docs/gemini-3?thinking=high">how to use it here</a>.</p>
<p>I wanted to try it out for scientific applications.</p>
<section id="science-cartoon-with-web-search-grounding" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="science-cartoon-with-web-search-grounding">Science cartoon with web search grounding</h2>
<p>I ran this prompt for <a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/aqc.70242">a very recent study</a> that was only just published, so well beyond the cut-off data for inclusion in the model’s training data:</p>
<pre><code>Make a comic strip explaining key findings of the study: 'Predicting the impact of giant kelp restoration on food webs and fisheries production'. Use a cartoon style similar to spongebob squarepants, but dont use any spongebob characters that violate copyright. Instead make the characters a fish, a rock lobster and an abalone.</code></pre>
<p><img src="https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2025-11-23-exploring-gemini-3-image-generation/study-cartoon2.jpeg" style="max-height: 600px; width: auto;"></p>
<p>This study was published after the model’s cutoff data for inclusion of training data, so it is a useful test of the search grounding capabilities. It gets the details right, though urchin barrens aren’t the main cause of the giant kelp decline and kelp normally grows on rocks, not sand.</p>
<p>My original attempt didn’t include the statement about copyright and it made an image that included Spongebob and his friends - some work for Google to do here if they are going to avoid copyright violations.</p>
<pre><code>Make a comic strip explaining key findings of the study: 'Predicting the impact of giant kelp restoration on food webs and fisheries production'. Use a cartoon style similar to spongebob squarepants.</code></pre>
</section>
<section id="infographics-with-grounding" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="infographics-with-grounding">Infographics with grounding</h2>
<p>I ran this prompt that asks for an infographic for <a href="https://besjournals.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1111/2041-210X.70105">my recent study</a>.</p>
<pre><code>Make an infographic explaining the new research study 'Assessing predictive accuracy of species abundance models in dynamic systems' published in Methods in Ecology and Evolution </code></pre>
<p>Here’s the result</p>
<p><img src="https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2025-11-23-exploring-gemini-3-image-generation/study-infographic.jpeg" style="max-height: 600px; width: auto;"></p>
<p>Which is 100% accurate. The only thing I’d change would be to add the study’s DOI to the infographic.</p>
</section>
<section id="r-code" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="r-code">R code</h2>
<p>Here’s an example of visual reasoning. Here we ask the model to generate an image of R code with resulting plot:</p>
<pre><code>Generate an image of R code and a graph in an IDE. The code will show how to fit a linear regression to data. The graph will show temperature on the x-axis and # people of the y-axis. Title the graph Swimming in Tasmania</code></pre>
<p>The results show the model is capable of correctly interpreting the R code it wrote:</p>
<p><img src="https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2025-11-23-exploring-gemini-3-image-generation/rcode.jpg" style="max-height: 600px; width: auto;"></p>
<p>This is not a screen shot of an IDE (note the errors in the names of panels) but an image generated to represent a screenshot.</p>
</section>
<section id="visual-reasoning" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="visual-reasoning">Visual reasoning</h2>
<p>To further test the visual reasoning I set a more complex task of plotting some data that I specified, showing a GAM fit to that data and plotting the residuals.</p>
<pre><code>Generate a two panel plot created with the R program. Here is the data to use for the plots: `x &lt;- 1:10; y &lt;- c(5, 10, 11, 9, 15, 12, 13, 6, 3, 2)`. The first panel will show an x-y plot of the data, as well as a the fitted curve from a gam spline with 3 dimension basis function. The second panel will show the residuals of the model with a horizontal line at y=0. Show the plots as a single image with two panels side by side.</code></pre>
<p><img src="https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2025-11-23-exploring-gemini-3-image-generation/rcode-gam.jpeg" style="max-height: 500px; width: auto;"></p>
<p>This one got the data points approximately correct (blue points), but was off with the GAM fit and residuals. For example, according to its fitted curve (red) the first, second and third residuals (green points) should be at zero. Likewise the two final points should be at zero. For comparison, here’s the answer if I generate that with actual R code:</p>
<p><img src="https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2025-11-23-exploring-gemini-3-image-generation/gam_plot.jpg" style="max-height: 400px; width: auto;"></p>
<p>You can see the AI generated residual plot was well off the mark, both in terms of the residuals</p>
</section>
<section id="code-for-api-access" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="code-for-api-access">Code for API access</h2>
<p>At the moment the easiest way to use this model is via the Gemini chat platform, or via direct API calls.</p>
<p>Here’s an example of the Python code to use the Gemini API.</p>
<pre><code>from google import genai
from google.genai import types
import os
from dotenv import load_dotenv
load_dotenv()

api_key = os.getenv("GEMINI_API_KEY")

# The client gets the API key from the environment variable `GEMINI_API_KEY`.
client = genai.Client(api_key=api_key)

prompt = "Generate a two panel plot created with the R program. Here is the data to use for the plots: `x &lt;- 1:10; y &lt;- c(5, 10, 11, 9, 15, 12, 13, 6, 3, 2)`. The first panel will show an x-y plot of the data, as well as a the fitted curve from a gam spline with 3 dimension basis function. The second panel will show the residuals of the model with a horizontal line at y=0. Show the plots as a single image with two panels side by side. "
aspect_ratio = "3:4" # "1:1","2:3","3:2","3:4","4:3","4:5","5:4","9:16","16:9","21:9"

response = client.models.generate_content(
    model="gemini-3-pro-image-preview",
    contents=prompt,
    config=types.GenerateContentConfig(
        response_modalities=['Text', 'Image'],
        image_config=types.ImageConfig(
            aspect_ratio=aspect_ratio,
        )#,
        #tools=[{"google_search": {}}]
    )
)

for part in response.parts:
    if part.text is not None:
        print(part.text)
    elif image:= part.as_image():
        image.save("temp/rcode.png")</code></pre>
<p>I’ve commented out the web search grounding. Uncomment that if you want to ground your search.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>rstats</category>
  <category>genAI</category>
  <guid>https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2025-11-23-exploring-gemini-3-image-generation/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 13:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>When a species’ fate hangs on survey design</title>
  <link>https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2025-11-21-survey-design-endangered-species/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Survey design can be one of those dry academic topics that students shy away from. So I wanted to highlight the sad case of the Greater Glider, a gliding possum.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://theconversation.com/new-logging-rules-in-nsw-put-the-greater-glider-closer-to-extinction-when-will-we-start-protecting-these-amazing-animals-223182">greater glider is on its way to extinction</a> thanks in part due to insufficient survey designs.</p>
<p>As a protected species there are buffer zones for logging around <em>known</em> greater glider habitat. The buffers are bigger still if a glider den (tree hollow) is confirmed. The “known” part is where survey design comes in.</p>
<p>The problem is, current survey designs are <a href="https://www.abc.net.au/news/2025-11-21/environment-groups-decry-greater-glider-survey-results/106017274">not sufficient to reliably detect greater gliders</a>.</p>
<p>Gliders emerge from their dens around sunset then go out to forage.</p>
<p>Official surveys are limited to roads and to a short period around sunset. But this means they will miss glider dens that aren’t near roads. That’s also a very limited amount of time to spot a cryptic species.</p>
<p>The quality of the official survey design is indicated by the fact that citizen scientists found 918 gliders in an area where the official survey only found 42.</p>
<p>From a statistical viewpoint the official survey design potentially suffers from two issues:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Bias, in that only habitats near roads are surveyed</li>
<li>Low detection rates, in that the time surveyed is too limited.</li>
</ol>
<p>Below I want to illustrate the detectability aspect, as its obvious how you deal with the bias aspect (do more complete surveys of the area).</p>
<p><img src="https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2025-11-21-survey-design-endangered-species/possum.jpg" class="img-fluid"> Brushtail possum considering its detectability model (AI generated image).</p>
<section id="detectability" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="detectability">Detectability</h2>
<p>In ecology we use repeat surveys to estimate a species’ detectability.</p>
<p>Detectability is a key parameter to estimate and then to account for when designing surveys.</p>
<p>Let me show you with a simple simulation how repeat surveys dramatically improve your chances of detecting a species that’s actually present.</p>
<div class="cell">
<div class="cell-output-display">
<div>
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2025-11-21-survey-design-endangered-species/index_files/figure-html/detection-simulation-1.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="672"></p>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>The simulation shows a dramatic improvement in detection probability with repeat surveys.</p>
<p>Estimating the detectability parameter can be complicated with real world survey designs. But the good news is that it is a well researched area of ecology and many frameworks (with handy R packages) exist to help you. Using these methods is a must for cryptic species.</p>
</section>
<section id="survey-design-matters" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="survey-design-matters">Survey design matters</h2>
<p>Issues of survey design often come up in environmental controversies. Its an important area for conservation biologists to study and to learn well. They need to know the principles so they can make a strong case for survey designs that are sufficient to protect endangered species.</p>
<p>Let’s hope that the survey design for gliders can be turned around, as conservationists are advocating for, so we can save this unique Australian mammal.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>research</category>
  <guid>https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2025-11-21-survey-design-endangered-species/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 13:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Should I post my manuscript to a pre-print server?</title>
  <link>https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2025-11-15-should-i-do-a-pre-print/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>In our recent lab meeting we <a href="https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2018-08-20-biorxiv-pre-print-posting-guide/index.html">revisited the topic of pre-prints and pre-print servers</a> to answer the question - should I post a pre-print of my manuscript?</p>
<p>Thanks to Jordan Holdorf for helping me write this post and Matt Holden for contributions via linkedin.</p>
<p>In a recent lab meeting, we revisited the question: Should I post a preprint of my manuscript? A few years ago, <a href="https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2018-08-20-biorxiv-pre-print-posting-guide/index.html">I wrote about this topic after posting my fourth preprint to bioRxiv</a>. Since then, the landscape has shifted, and our discussion—thanks to Jordan Holdorf for the notes—highlighted new considerations worth sharing.</p>
<p><img src="https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2025-11-15-should-i-do-a-pre-print/pre-print-illustration.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>*Generated by Google Gemini.</p>
<section id="what-are-preprints" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-are-preprints">What Are Preprints?</h2>
<p>Preprints are manuscripts shared publicly before formal peer review. They’re free to post, free to read, and usually come with a DOI, making them citable. Popular servers include arXiv, bioRxiv, EcoEvoRxiv, medRxiv, and SSRN.</p>
<p>The concept isn’t new, arXiv launched in physics back in 1991, but preprints surged during COVID-19 as scientists raced to share findings quickly. Conservation science and ecology have increasingly embraced preprints as well.</p>
</section>
<section id="why-bother-pros-and-cons" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-bother-pros-and-cons">Why Bother? Pros and Cons</h2>
<section id="pros" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pros">Pros</h3>
<ul>
<li>Visibility and speed: Your work is accessible immediately, not months later.</li>
<li>Feedback: Pre-review comments can strengthen your paper.</li>
<li>Citations: Preprints can be cited, even if the journal version is paywalled.</li>
<li>Priority: Posting establishes your claim to an idea.</li>
<li>Flexibility: You can build on work that’s still under review.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="cons" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="cons">Cons</h3>
<ul>
<li>Quality concerns: Preprints aren’t peer-reviewed, so errors can spread.</li>
<li>Misinformation risk: Especially if high-profile topics get picked up by the press.</li>
<li>Version confusion: If titles change, citations may split across versions.</li>
<li>Journal policies: Most journals now allow preprints, but check first.</li>
<li>Double-blind issues: Reviewers can find your preprint and identify authors.</li>
<li>Time cost: Uploading and revising adds extra steps.</li>
<li>Google Scholar may not list your published article for up to 6 months after publication (rather than the normal few days delay after publishing). This is a known issue with pre-prints on SSRN and bioRxiv, apparently fixed for arxiv pre-prints.</li>
</ul>
<p>Overall, the benefits usually outweigh the drawbacks—if you manage the process carefully.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="key-considerations" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="key-considerations">Key considerations</h2>
<p>Some lab members expressed concern that their work could get stolen from a pre-print and published by an other author. I would think this is rare, however, with AI making it increasingly easy to paraphrase other people’s work, the risk is probably higher than it used to be.</p>
<p>We decided that if you are concerned about plagiarism, it is best not to link your open code repository in the preprint. That could make it too easy for a bad actor to create a new version of your work.</p>
<p>Media is another factor. Journalists generally prefer to cover peer-reviewed work, though during COVID, preprints made headlines. For most fields, you can expect little media attention until formal publication. This is good, as peer review is crucial for credibility.</p>
<p>Finally, think strategically. Preprints make sense for urgent topics, methods papers, or when you want community feedback. They’re less practical if you’re under time pressure or working on a niche topic.</p>
</section>
<section id="how-to-post-a-preprint" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-to-post-a-preprint">How to Post a Preprint</h2>
<p>Here’s a streamlined guide based on experience and Jordan’s notes:</p>
<ul>
<li>Finish the manuscript and get coauthor approval. Check your target journal’s preprint policy.</li>
<li>Format carefully. Upload a polished PDF with clear figures, tables, and your contact info.</li>
<li>Sign up for a server and ORCID. ORCID helps link your work across platforms.</li>
<li>Choose a license. Think about reuse—Creative Commons options vary.</li>
<li>Upload and wait. Most servers take ~24 hours to post.</li>
<li>Share strategically. Share on social media (to other scientists, not for general public), email colleagues, or post on Google Scholar if you want feedback.</li>
<li>Revise before acceptance. Once your paper is accepted, most servers block updates. Link the final version. Matching titles help merge citations; otherwise, see the server’s instructions for how to fix the connection.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="my-experience" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="my-experience">My Experience</h2>
<p>I’ve had mixed results. One preprint was redundant because the journal review was lightning-fast. Another has been cited multiple times while stuck in review purgatory—proof that preprints can keep your work alive. The biggest headache? Title changes. If your published title differs, make sure the preprint links correctly.</p>
</section>
<section id="final-thoughts" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts</h2>
<p>Preprints aren’t a magic bullet, but they’re a powerful tool when used thoughtfully. They accelerate science, increase visibility, and invite collaboration—but they also demand care around version control, anonymity, and journal policies.</p>
<p>On the balance of it I use them selectively. For work that is time-sensitive, methodologically important, or where I want feedback, then I do a pre-print. If I’m busy or there is little to gain, then I skip it.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>research-skills</category>
  <guid>https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2025-11-15-should-i-do-a-pre-print/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 13:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Upcoming R workshops in Brisbane February 2026</title>
  <link>https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2025-11-14-upcoming-R-workshop-brisbane/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>R workshops in Brisbane Australia, February 2026.</p>
<p>For many years I had the pleasure of teaching with Ant Richardson and the team for these R workshops. I’m not there anymore, but recommend attending these if you can make the dates:</p>
<p><img src="https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2025-11-14-upcoming-R-workshop-brisbane/r-workshop-uq.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
<p>Transform your research questions into robust statistical insights with our 2026 Summer R Workshops in an immersive exploration of R programming and statistical modelling. These workshops in February 2026 are designed for beginners and researchers who want to build a solid foundation in R programming and progress through to advanced statistical techniques. Whether you’re completely new to R or looking to strengthen your statistical modelling skills, join us to develop the analytical expertise essential for modern research!</p>
<p>Registration is now open. For more information, see our website https://mathmarecol.github.io/RWorkshop/summer.html and the attached flyer. For any questions, email cbcs-workshops@uq.edu.au.</p>
<p>Testimonials: “I truly enjoyed the whole workshop. Great teachers, really nice real data examples and good notes and background” “I am feeling a lot better about using stats now than I was previously” “I think it should be a compulsory course for all PhDs”</p>



 ]]></description>
  <category>rstats</category>
  <guid>https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2025-11-14-upcoming-R-workshop-brisbane/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 13:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Its easy to make your own AI agent in R</title>
  <link>https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2025-11-10-make-an-ai-agent-in-r/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>There’s a lot of hype about AI agents, but buried under the hype there is a really simple architecture. I got inspired by <a href="https://fly.io/blog/everyone-write-an-agent/">this post that points out how easy it is to make an AI agent</a>.</p>
<p>In this post I’ll show how to make an agent in R with the <a href="https://ellmer.tidyverse.org/"><code>ellmer</code> package</a>.</p>
<p>A large language model agent is a <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Sep/18/agents/">large language models that can run tools in a loop</a>.</p>
<p>Tools give the agent powers to take actions like read data, create files, access the internet. Anything software task you can think of really.</p>
<p>Here’s the cool thing, the ‘run tools in a loop’ architecture is simple. Building an AI (the LLM) is really complex and super expensive (like cost of $100 millions). But you can easily get access to 100s of these LLMs cheaply via API calls. Then its easy to plug them into DIY agents.</p>
<p>The simplicity means you can create just about anything you can dream up.</p>
<p>Let’s make an agent that reads R help files. A chat agent could give better advice if it read the up-to-date R help files first.</p>
<section id="chatting-with-llms-from-rs" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="chatting-with-llms-from-rs">Chatting with LLMs from Rs</h2>
<div class="code-copy-outer-scaffold"><div class="sourceCode" id="cb1" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb1-1"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">library</span>(ellmer)</span></code></pre></div></div>
<p>Set up an <a href="https://www.seascapemodels.org/AI-assistants-for-scientific-coding/03-set-up.html#sec-apikeys">API key with the provider</a> you choose and you can easily talk to a large language model with ellmer:</p>
<div class="code-copy-outer-scaffold"><div class="sourceCode" id="cb2" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb2-1">chat <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">chat_anthropic</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">model =</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"claude-haiku-4-5"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb2-2">chat<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">$</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">chat</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"How do I do a regression in R?"</span>)</span></code></pre></div></div>
<p>We can then string together a chat:</p>
<div class="code-copy-outer-scaffold"><div class="sourceCode" id="cb3" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb3-1">chat <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">chat_anthropic</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">model =</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"claude-haiku-4-5"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb3-2">turn1 <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> chat<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">$</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">chat</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"How do I do a regression in R?"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb3-3">turn2 <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> chat<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">$</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">chat</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"Show how to verify the model."</span>)</span></code></pre></div></div>
<p>The way a multi-turn conversation works is that on the second turn the entire conversation thread (system message, user message, assistant message, new user message) is sent back to the LLM at each turn.</p>
<p>Repeated calls to <code>chat</code> just manage that for us.</p>
<p>The LLM talking to itself isn’t very useful, we can use tools to inject new information into the conversation.</p>
</section>
<section id="create-a-tool-to-read-a-help-file" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="create-a-tool-to-read-a-help-file">Create a tool to read a help file</h2>
<p>The tool has two parts: (1) An R script that does something; (2) a specification that tells the LLM how to use the tool.</p>
<section id="r-function" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="r-function">R function</h3>
<div class="code-copy-outer-scaffold"><div class="sourceCode" id="cb4" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb4-1">read_help_as_text <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">function</span>(topic, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">pkg =</span> <span class="cn" style="color: #8f5902;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">NULL</span>) {</span>
<span id="cb4-2">    h <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> utils<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">::</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">help</span>(topic, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">package =</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">eval</span>(pkg))</span>
<span id="cb4-3">    <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">if</span> (<span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">length</span>(h) <span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">==</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">0</span>) <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">stop</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"Help topic not found"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb4-4">    rd <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> utils<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">:::</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.getHelpFile</span>(h)             </span>
<span id="cb4-5">    txt <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">paste</span>(<span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">capture.output</span>(tools<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">::</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">Rd2txt</span>(rd)), <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">collapse =</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">\n</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb4-6">    <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">return</span>(txt)</span>
<span id="cb4-7">}</span></code></pre></div></div>
<p>This R function takes a topic and optionally a package name. It then returns the relevant help file as a string</p>
<div class="code-copy-outer-scaffold"><div class="sourceCode" id="cb5" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb5-1">help_txt <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">read_help_as_text</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"lm"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb5-2"><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">cat</span>(<span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">substr</span>(help_txt, <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span>, <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1000</span>), <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">\n</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"</span>) </span></code></pre></div></div>
</section>
<section id="tool-definition" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tool-definition">Tool definition</h3>
<p>The tool definition tells the LLM how to use the read_help_as_text tool.</p>
<div class="code-copy-outer-scaffold"><div class="sourceCode" id="cb6" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb6-1">read_help_as_text <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">tool</span>(</span>
<span id="cb6-2">  read_help_as_text,</span>
<span id="cb6-3">  <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.description =</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"Returns an R help file as a string"</span>,</span>
<span id="cb6-4">  <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">topic =</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">type_string</span>(</span>
<span id="cb6-5">      <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"R function or topic"</span>,</span>
<span id="cb6-6">      <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">required =</span> <span class="cn" style="color: #8f5902;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">TRUE</span></span>
<span id="cb6-7">    ),</span>
<span id="cb6-8">    <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">pkg =</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">type_string</span>(</span>
<span id="cb6-9">      <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"R package to get help file from"</span>,</span>
<span id="cb6-10">      <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">required =</span> <span class="cn" style="color: #8f5902;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">FALSE</span></span>
<span id="cb6-11">    )</span>
<span id="cb6-12">)</span></code></pre></div></div>
</section>
<section id="using-the-tool" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="using-the-tool">Using the tool</h3>
<div class="code-copy-outer-scaffold"><div class="sourceCode" id="cb7" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb7-1">chat <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">chat_anthropic</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">model =</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"claude-haiku-4-5"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb7-2">chat<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">$</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">register_tool</span>(read_help_as_text)</span>
<span id="cb7-3"></span>
<span id="cb7-4">chat<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">$</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">chat</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"Quote the definition of residuals from the lm() function, don't provide any other explanation or code"</span>)</span></code></pre></div></div>
<pre><code>"residuals: the residuals, that is response minus fitted values."</code></pre>
<p>That’s a pointless use case, but it demonstrates the tool is working. You can check the chat log to see when the tool was called:</p>
<div class="code-copy-outer-scaffold"><div class="sourceCode" id="cb9" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb9-1">chat</span></code></pre></div></div>
<pre><code>&lt;Chat Anthropic/claude-haiku-4-5 turns=4 tokens=4529/77&gt;
── user [626] ──────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────
Quote the definition of residuals from the lm() function, don't provide any other explanation or code
── assistant [59] ──────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────
[tool request (toolu_)]: read_help_as_text(topic = "lm")
── user [3218] ─────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────
[tool result  (toolu_)]:
...
     
── assistant [18] ──────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────
"residuals: the residuals, that is response minus fitted values."</code></pre>
</section>
</section>
<section id="getting-advice-on-recent-packages" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="getting-advice-on-recent-packages">Getting advice on recent packages</h2>
<p>LLMs often get tripped up if you ask them for code for niche or very recent packages. The <a href="https://zobaer09.github.io/FakeDataR/"><code>FakeDataR</code> package</a> is a recently released package that helps you make synthetic data to use with LLMs (if you are concerned about privacy of your real data).</p>
<p>If you ask an LLM to use this package, it will tend to hallucinate a response, that won’t work. With our tool however, it can create accurate code:</p>
<div class="code-copy-outer-scaffold"><div class="sourceCode" id="cb11" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb11-1">chat <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">chat_anthropic</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">model =</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"claude-haiku-4-5"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb11-2">chat<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">$</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">register_tool</span>(read_help_as_text)</span>
<span id="cb11-3"></span>
<span id="cb11-4">chat<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">$</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">chat</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"How to use the generate_fake_data function from the R package FakeDataR to make a synthetic copy of mtcars"</span>)</span></code></pre></div></div>
<pre><code>I'll help you find information about the `generate_fake_data` function from the
FakeDataR package.

◯ [tool call] read_help_as_text(pkg = "FakeDataR", topic =
"generate_fake_data")
...

Great! Now I can show you how to use `generate_fake_data` to create a synthetic
copy of the `mtcars` dataset. Here's how to do it:

## Basic Usage

```r
# Install FakeDataR if you haven't already
# install.packages("FakeDataR")

library(FakeDataR)

# Generate synthetic data from mtcars
synthetic_mtcars &lt;- generate_fake_data(
  data = mtcars,
  n = 32  # Create same number of rows as original mtcars
)

# View the result
head(synthetic_mtcars)
```

## More Detailed Examples
...
The resulting synthetic dataset preserves the structure and statistical 
properties of the original while being completely artificial!</code></pre>
</section>
<section id="creating-an-agentic-loop" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="creating-an-agentic-loop">Creating an agentic loop</h2>
<p>Let’s add one more tool to show how they can be chained together to build the beginnings of an agentic loop.</p>
<p>This tool will grab the R code from the markdown code blocks in the LLMs response, then write it to a file.</p>
<p>First the function definition:</p>
<div class="code-copy-outer-scaffold"><div class="sourceCode" id="cb13" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb13-1">write_r_code <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">function</span>(rcode){</span>
<span id="cb13-2">    code_blocks <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> stringr<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">::</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">str_extract_all</span>(rcode, <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"```r</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">\\</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">s*([</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">\\</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">s</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">\\</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">S]*?)```"</span>)[[<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span>]]</span>
<span id="cb13-3">    code <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">paste</span>(stringr<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">::</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">str_replace_all</span>(code_blocks, <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"```r</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">\\</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">s*|```"</span>, <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">""</span>), <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">collapse =</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">\n</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb13-4">    <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">writeLines</span>(code, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">con =</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"temp_code.R"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb13-5">    <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">return</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"R code written to temp_code.R"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb13-6">}</span></code></pre></div></div>
<p>Now the tool definition:</p>
<div class="code-copy-outer-scaffold"><div class="sourceCode" id="cb14" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb14-1">write_r_code <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">tool</span>(</span>
<span id="cb14-2">  write_r_code,</span>
<span id="cb14-3">  <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.description =</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"Writes R code contained in markdown code blocks to a file."</span>,</span>
<span id="cb14-4">  <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">rcode =</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">type_string</span>(</span>
<span id="cb14-5">      <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"Character string containing R code in markdown code blocks"</span>,</span>
<span id="cb14-6">      <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">required =</span> <span class="cn" style="color: #8f5902;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">TRUE</span></span>
<span id="cb14-7">    )</span>
<span id="cb14-8">)</span></code></pre></div></div>
<p>Now we just register both tools and start our chat.</p>
<div class="code-copy-outer-scaffold"><div class="sourceCode" id="cb15" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb15-1">chat <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">chat_anthropic</span>(<span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">model =</span>  <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"claude-haiku-4-5"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb15-2">chat<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">$</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">register_tool</span>(read_help_as_text)</span>
<span id="cb15-3">chat<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">$</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">register_tool</span>(write_r_code)</span>
<span id="cb15-4"></span>
<span id="cb15-5">chat_out <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> chat<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">$</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">chat</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"Use generate_fake_data function from the R package FakeDataR to make a single synthetic version of mtcars. "</span>)</span></code></pre></div></div>
<p><code>ellmer</code> will pass the results of the tool call back to the LLM, which can decide to call more tools if needed. Inspecting the chat log shows the sequence of tool calls, with no user intervention required.</p>
</section>
<section id="tuning-agents" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tuning-agents">Tuning agents</h2>
<p>The write R code tool worked, some of the time… Other times it wrote a blank file. There’s a lot of niggly details to making agents work reliably, including choosing a powerful enough LLM, writing a system prompt that guides tool use, and writing powerful but secure tools.</p>
<p>If I was going to take this example further I could add a function to run the Rscript that was created, that might require some extra security considerations (see below for one example).</p>
<p>Going further I would also work on system prompt that provided guidance to the LLM on its role and how to approach problems. There’s many open source system prompts out there that I could draw on to create this.</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>Its an exciting time to be working on AI agents. The field is so new you can easily make new discoveries and be ahead of even world leading AI labs.</p>
<p>An example. Scott Spillias, a postdoc at CSIRO, developed an agent framework that uses an evolutionary algorithm to write math to <a href="https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2025.07.14.664628v1.abstract">create ecosystem models</a>. He showed the agent could create models that are great at predicting out-of-sample data, and that have biologically meaningful parameters.</p>
<p>A month or so after he published his pre-print, the Google DeepMind team published a similar idea of using LLM evolutionary algorithms to generate scientific models.</p>
<p>I look forwards to seeing what the R community creates with agents.</p>
</section>
<section id="example-of-using-tool_reject-for-user-permission" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="example-of-using-tool_reject-for-user-permission">Example of using tool_reject for user permission</h2>
<p>Check out <code>?tool_reject</code> for a way to require user permission before tools are used. Here’s how to implement that in our <code>write_r_code</code> function.</p>
<div class="code-copy-outer-scaffold"><div class="sourceCode" id="cb16" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode r code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode r"><span id="cb16-1">write_r_code <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">function</span>(rcode){</span>
<span id="cb16-2">  allow_read <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> utils<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">::</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">askYesNo</span>(</span>
<span id="cb16-3">    <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"Would you like to allow access to write files?"</span></span>
<span id="cb16-4">  )</span>
<span id="cb16-5">  <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">if</span> (<span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">isTRUE</span>(allow_read)) {</span>
<span id="cb16-6">    code_blocks <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> stringr<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">::</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">str_extract_all</span>(rcode, <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"```r</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">\\</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">s*([</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">\\</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">s</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">\\</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">S]*?)```"</span>)[[<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span>]]</span>
<span id="cb16-7">    code <span class="ot" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;-</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">paste</span>(stringr<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">::</span><span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">str_replace_all</span>(code_blocks, <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"```r</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">\\</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">s*|```"</span>, <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">""</span>), <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">collapse =</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">\n</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb16-8">    <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">writeLines</span>(code, <span class="at" style="color: #657422;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">con =</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"temp_code.R"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb16-9">    <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">return</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"R code written to temp_code.R"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb16-10">  } <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">else</span> {</span>
<span id="cb16-11">    <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">tool_reject</span>()</span>
<span id="cb16-12">  } </span>
<span id="cb16-13">}</span></code></pre></div></div>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>rstats</category>
  <category>genAI</category>
  <guid>https://www.seascapemodels.org/posts/2025-11-10-make-an-ai-agent-in-r/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 13:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
